Guide to the Herman and Margarett Root Brown Family Papers, 1890-2016, bulk dates 1940-1965 MS 697
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Herman and Margarett Root Brown Family Papers
1890-2016
1940-1965
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Sarofim, Louisa Stude
MS 697
1.5 Linear Feet 2 boxes
The collection consists of a range of keepsakes memorializing the lives of Herman and Margarett Root Brown and their family. The oldest in time are the high school senior class yearbook of Herman Brown and a framed loan document bearing his signature. There are many photographs, both formal portraits and small snapshots as well as intermediate size pictures. Among the people featured in addition to Herman, Margarett, and their children are the mother and sisters of Herman and George Brown, the wife and daughters of George, and some business associates.
Biographical / Historical
Herman Brown, born in Belton, Texas in 1892, and Margarett Root, born in 1895, were married in 1917. Having begun doing construction work in Belton in 1914 and being paid in used equipment and mules, Herman formed a business which his brother-in-law Dan Root joined in 1919. They were in turn joined by Herman's younger brother George in 1922. For the first twenty years their work was primarily road paving and bridge building throughout Texas. In 1942, with federal government involvement through freshman congressman Lyndon Baines Johnson, they completed a 1.3-mile-long dam near Austin.
World War II prompted the company's expansion into ship-building, and it produced 359 destroyer escorts and other ship types. After the war Brown and Root expanded by acquiring (for $143 million) the U.S. government's Big Inch and Little Big Inch pipelines (originally built to replace tanker ships vulnerable to German submarines).
In 1951 Herman and George Brown and their wives set up the Brown Foundation, which has made large gifts beginning with Rice University, Southwestern University (Margarett Root Brown's alma mater), and the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston.
Two children joined the family of Herman and Margarett Brown, who had no children of their own. Louisa and Michael Stude were adopted and raised by the Browns but kept their birth names because their natural parents were still living.
Herman Brown died on November 15, 1962, and Margarett followed in 1963. To honor the memory of Margarett, George Brown and his wife Alice donated funds used to establish a residential college at Rice University. Margarett Root Brown College was dedicated October 3, 1965.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of a range of keepsakes memorializing the lives of Herman and Margarett Root Brown and their family. The oldest in time are the high school senior class yearbook of Herman Brown and a framed loan document bearing his signature. There are many photographs, both formal portraits and small snapshots as well as intermediate size pictures. Among the people featured in addition to Herman, Margarett, and their children are the mother and sisters of Herman and George Brown, the wife and daughters of George, and some business associates.
Related to Herman Brown's business achievements are an article published in Fortune Magazine and proclamations from the Texas House of Representatives and Senate honoring him at the time of his death.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These materials were donated by the Brown Foundation and Louisa Stude Sarofim in 2016.
Related Materials
Brown and Root archives, MS 466, Woodson Research Center Builders: Herman and George Brown Book Research Files, MS 464, Woodson Research Center
Index Terms
Subjects
Business
Document Types
photographs; letters (correspondence); documents
Subjects (Persons)
Brown, Herman,1892-1962; Brown, Margarett Root; Sarofim, Louisa Stude; Brown family
Subjects (Corporations)
Brown Foundation
- Series I: Brown family papers and photographs, 1890-2016
  - Bank loan document signed by Herman Brown, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Herman Brown's high school senior yearbook, 1911
  - Early history of Brown and Root, by Brown Booth, nephew of Herman and George, pre-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Herman Brown honors: Honorary Doctor of Law, Southwestern University, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs used in ancestry book of Louisa Stude Sarofim, 1925-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Louisa Stude photographs, 1944-1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Christmas photograph, Alice Brown's family, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Herman Brown photograph, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Margarett Root Brown photographs, 1920-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Brown and Root family members – several generations, 1900-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of ancestors of Louisa Stude Sarofim and others, 1890-1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Publications about Browns and Louisa Stude Sarofim, 1957-2016 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters from a sheep rancher (on Brown property?), 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Brown and Root family members, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series II: Oversize photographs and documents, 1925-1963
  - Margarett Root Brown photograph, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Herman Brown photograph, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Herman Brown, Jim Abercrombie, and unidentified person, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bannie Brown photograph, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Louisa and Mike Stude photograph, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Louisa Stude photograph, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fortune Magazine article featuring Herman and George Brown, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Resolutions of Texas Senate and Texas House of Representatives honoring Brown, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)